Chapter 66.
The Shark Massacre.
When in the southern fishery a captured sperm whale, after long and weary toil,
is brought alongside late at night, it is not, as a general thing, at least
customary to proceed at once to the business of cutting him in, for that
business is an exceedingly laborious one, is not very soon completed, and
requires all hands to set about it.
Therefore, the common usage is to take in all sail, lash the helm ale, and then
send everyone below to his hammock till daylight, with the reservation that
until that time anchor watches shall be kept, that is, two and two for an hour
each couple, the crew in rotation shall mount the deck to see that all goes
well. But sometimes, especially upon the line in the Pacific, this plan will not
answer at all, because such incalculable hosts of sharks gather around the mured
carcass that were he left so for 6 hours, say, on a stretch, little more
than the skeleton would be visible by morning. In most other parts of the
ocean, however, where these fish do not so largely abound, their wondrous
veracity can be at times considerably diminished by vigorously stirring them
up with sharp wailing spades, a procedure notwithstanding which in some
instances only seems to tickle them into still greater activity. But it was not
thus in the present case with the Peekquad sharks, though to be sure any
man unaccustomed to such sights to have looked over her side that night would
have almost thought the whole round sea was one huge cheese and those sharks the
maggots in it. Nevertheless, upon Stubs setting the anchor watch after his
supper was concluded, and when, accordingly, Quiquake and a folkal
seaman came on deck, no small excitement was created among the sharks, for
immediately suspending the cutting stages over the side, and lowering three
lanterns so that they cast long gleams of light over the turbid seas, these two
mariners, darting their long wailing spades, kept up an incessant murdering
of the sharks by striking ing the keen steel deep into their skulls, seemingly
their only vital part.
Footnote: The whailing spade used for cutting in is made of the very best
steel, is about the bigness of a man's spread hand, and in general shape
corresponds to the garden implement after which it is named, only its sides
are perfectly flat, and its upper end considerably narrower than the lower.
This weapon is always kept as sharp as possible and when being used is
occasionally honed just like a razor. In its socket a stiff pole from 20 to 30 ft
long is inserted for a handle end of footnote. But in the foamy confusion of
their mixed and struggling hosts, the marksmen could not always hit their
mark, and this brought about new revelations of the incredible ferocity
of the foe. They viciously snapped not only at each other's disembowelments,
but like flexible bows, bent round and bit their own, till those entrails
seemed swallowed over and over again by the same mouth, to be oppositely voided
by the gaping wound. Nor was this all.
It was unsafe to meddle with the corpses and ghosts of these creatures. A sort of
generic or pantheistic vitality seemed to lurk in their very joints and bones
after what might be called the individual life had departed. Killed and
hoisted on deck for the sake of his skin, one of these sharks almost took
poor Quiquake's hand off when he tried to shut down the dead lid of his murderous jaw.
Quiqu no care what god made him shark said the savage agonizingly lifting his
hand up and down whether Fiji god or nantucket god but to god what made shark
must be one damn engine